Finding Aid for the Arthur J. O. Anderson papers LSC.2133
UCLA Library Special Collections
Arthur J.O. Anderson papers
1892-1998
UCLA Library Special Collections
Anderson, Arthur J. O.
LSC.2133
58 Linear Feet (53 record cartons, 3 document boxes, 1 oversize flat box, 1 telescope box)
Arthur James Outram Anderson was a professor and researcher whose specializations included the American Southwest, Mesoamerica, and the Nahuatl language. Anderson's most significant work that defined his professional career was his collaboration with colleague Charles E. Dibble, of the University of Utah, on their English translation of the Aztec language Florentine Codex. The collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, publications, typescripts, scrapbooks, maps, photographs, slides, microfilm, negatives and notes related to his work as a professor, researcher, editor and translator.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
This collection was a gift of Elizabeth F. Klotz, 1999.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9971508783606533
Biography/History
Arthur James Outram Anderson was born in Phoenix, Arizona on November 26, 1907 and raised in Guadalajara, Mexico before he returned to the United States for his college and graduate education. He received a B.A. in English from San Diego State College in 1930, an M.A. in Anthropology from Claremont Colleges in 1931, and a Ph.D. in Anthropology from the University of Southern California in 1940.
During his professional career, Anderson worked as a professor and researcher largely in the field of Anthropology. He taught at Occidental College, Eastern New Mexico, and San Diego State University, among other schools, and served as director of the Roosevelt County Museum in New Mexico and curator of history and director of publications at the Museum of New Mexico in Santa Fe. His specializations included the American Southwest, Mesoamerica, and the Nahuatl language.
The most significant work that defined his professional career was Anderson's collaboration with colleague Charles E. Dibble, of the University of Utah, on their English translation of the Aztec language Florentine Codex. The Florentine Codex is a 16th century Nahuatl language document written by Fray Bernardino de Sahagun, a Spanish missionary who documented contemporary Aztec life in conquest-era Mexico. Sahagun's work, also known by the title Historia general de las cosas de Nueva Espana, was drafted between the years 1545 and 1590 and documented Aztec rituals, customs, language, and society during the Spanish conquest of Mexico.
Anderson and Dibble were the first anthropologists to translate and publish the primary resource codex from Nahuatl to English, a major translation project that spanned more than 30 years, from 1948-1982. In recognition of their achievement, the President of Mexico conferred upon them, the Order of the Aztec Eagle, with rank of Commander in 1981 and then in 1984, the King of Spain conferred upon them, the Order of Isabel la Católica, with the rank of Knight Commander.
Anderson's other major publications include:
Anderson, Arthur J. O. Grammatical examples, exercises, & review: for use with Rules of the Aztec language. Salt Lake City: University of Utah Press, 1973.
Anderson, Arthur J. O. Rules of the Aztec language: classicial Nahuatl grammar. A Translation by Arthur J. O. Anderson, with modifications, of Francisco Xavier Clavijer's Reglas de la lengua mexicana. Salt Lake City: University of Utah Press, 1973.
Clavijero, Francesco Saverio. Reglas de la lengua Mexicana con un vocabulario. Edición, introdución, paleografía y notas de Arthur J. O. Anderson; prefacio de Miguel León-Portillo. Mexico: Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México, Instituto de Investigaciones Históricas, 1974.
In addition to Anderson's collaboration with Charles Dibble, his bibliography includes joint publications with James Lockhart, Frances Berdan, Susan Schroeder, Barry Sell, Wayne Ruwet, Spencer Rogers and Thelma D. Sullivan. When Sullivan died, leaving her translation of Sahagun's Primeros Memoriales unfinished, Anderson completed it for her.
In addition, Anderson served as the Editor of El Palacio, the journal of The School of American Research and the Archaeological Society of New Mexico, from 1947-1957, and also served as the Associate Editor of the New Mexico Historical Review from 1946-1957.
In 1975 Anderson retired as professor emeritus from San Diego State University, where he served as a professor since 1961, and died on June 3, 1996.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, publications, typescripts, scrapbooks, maps, photographs, slides, microfilm, negatives and notes related to the career of Arthur J. O. Anderson. It includes materials related to Anderson's teaching and research on the Florentine Codex; Nahuatl language and grammar; Fray Bernardino de Sahagun; his service as the Editor of El Palacio and as the Associate Editor of the New Mexico Historical Review; monographs and serials from his research library; and material related to Anderson's receipt of Mexico's Order of the Aztec Eagle in 1981 and Spain's Order of Isabel la Católica in 1984.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection maintains the creator's original order. Boxes 1-33 comprise Anderson's personal papers and boxes 34-58 contain his research library.
- Correspondence, Publications and Research Files, 1937-1991 (Box 1)
  Scope and Content
  College catalogs and bulletins from Occidental, El Camino, San Diego State, and Eastern New Mexico. Periodicals from Mexico City and Madrid. "Of Interest To UCLA" folder of periodicals. Publications by Anderson, institutional correspondence to Anderson and a VHS tape titled Gpe. Hernandez: Rayos, Cosmos, Pregnancy, Misc. Cuentos Abelino Martinez: Talocan Cuentos, Tonalli Gpe Vásquez: Suplica Nemouhtil.
- Publications, 1938-1984 (Box 2)
  Publications include Anderson's Grammatical Examples, Exercises, & Review For Use with Rules of the Aztec Language with inscription to "Mary and Harry With Love, Arturo," The Hispanic American Historical Review, New Mexico Historical Review, New Scholar Volume 9, New Mexico Quarterly, Geographical Review, Studies Relating to Early Man in America by E.B. Howard, Environment and Native Subsistence Economies in the Central Great Plains By Waldo R. Wedel, "Conservation in Pueblo Architecture" by G.R. Stewart, "Prehistoric Trade in the Southwest" by Harold S. Colton, The Americas: A Quarterly Review of the Inter-American Cultural History, The Western Humanities Review, El Palacio: A Quarterly Journal of the Museum of New Mexico, Handbook of Latin American Studies, Seventy-Five Years of Latin American Research at the University of Texas, Boletin de la Sociedad Geografica de Lima, Current Topics in Aztec Studies: Essays in Honor of Dr. H.B. Nicholson, Discovery: A Monthly Publication of the San Diego Museum of Man, School of American Research of the Archaeological Institute of American Annual Reports, The School of American Research: Its Background, Its Future, Reglas de la Lengua Mexicana Con Un Vocabulario: Edicion, introduccion, paleografia y notas de Arthur J.O. Anderson, pamphlets from Instituto Jalisciense de Antropologia e Historia Guadalajara and an unbound notebook.
- Publications, 1940-1969 (Box 3)
  Copies of El Palacio, a review of the arts and sciences in the Southwest published by the School of American Research, the Museum of New Mexico, and the Archeological Society of New Mexico.
- Publications and Research Files, 1946-1994 (Box 4)
  Reprints of Anderson's articles from El Palacio. Copies of journals, magazines bibliographies, newsletters, catalogs and pamphlets. Sahagún research files including a copy of Charles Dibble's "The Nahuatlization of Christianity."
- Florentine Codex Index Cards, Undated (Box 5)
  Four boxes of Florentine Codex index cards which include Nahuatl language glossary with cross references.
- Florentine Codex Research Binders, Undated (Box 6)
  Six binders of manuscript and typescript Florentine Codex translations.
- Correspondence and Research Files, 1922-1986 (Box 7)
  Nine folders containing manuscript and typescript of the Tlaxcala Actas (1986), including related materials from Frances Berdan and James Lockhart. Correspondence with the University of Utah Press regarding contracts and publication of Florentine Codex. Course materials and Nahuatl bibliographies. Two notebooks of Nahuatl vocabulary translations, grammar, and etymology descriptions. Two of Anderson's scrapbooks entitled "Articles and Pictures on or about Anything Egyptian (Ancient Egyptian)" and "Everything Ancient Except Egyptian."
- Publications, 1971-1998 (Box 8)
  Publications including the following by Anderson: Codex Chimalpahin Volume 1 and 2, The Tlaxcalan Actas: A Compendium of the Records of the Cabildo of Tlaxcala (1545-1627), The War of Conquest: How It Was Waged Here in Mexico and Anderson's annotated working copies of Rules of the Aztec Language: A Translation and Grammatical Examples, Exercises, & Review For Use with Rules of the Aztec Language.
- Manuscripts and Typescripts, 1909-1980 (Box 9)
  Anderson and Charles Dibble's manuscripts and typescripts concerning "Sacred Songs" and "Coloquios." Dibble's typescript of the Codex "en Cruz." Anderson's annotated copy of Los Grandes Problemas Nacionales by Andres Molina Enriquez.
- Publications, 1892-1993 (Box 10)
  Books and other publications related to Prehispanic Mexico and translation of Aztec including the Codex Barbonicus and Anderson's "Temporary Foreword to the Florentine Codex, Books IV and V." Materials also include Anderson's annotated grammar books such as Carochi's Lengva Mexicana.
- Florentine Codex, 1950-1970 (Box 11)
  Complete set of Florentine Codex, translated from the Aztec into English with notes and illustrations by Anderson and Charles E. Dibble. This was Anderson's reference set with his annotations in the margins.
- Manuscripts and Correspondence, 1949-1996 (Box 12)
  Manuscripts and correspondence from Barry D. Sell on the Codex Chimalpahin. Anderson's "Favourite Celebrities" scrapbook of clippings. Anderson's copy of Brevarium Romanum. Proofs of "O My Beloved Children: Sahagun's Sermons to the Nahuas." First edition letterpress copy of Agnes C. Sims' "San Cristobal Petroglyphs." Folder of Congress of Americanists correspondence. Materials also include a folder of Anderson's illustrations for his return address labels.
- Manuscripts and Research Files, 1934-1966 (Box 13)
  Codex Chimalpahin manuscript. Syllabi and course readings from Anderson's doctoral work at USC, annotated copies of his Curriculum Vitae and a bound copy of his dissertation, "Eclipse Rituals and Procedures of North American Indians in Relation to Their Ceremonial Patterns, From the Point of View of Social Psychology." Research materials include a photocopy of a German language document on Aztecs and articles on Spanish Medicine.
- Publications, 1924-1979 (Box 14)
  Publications by Anderson and colleagues such as Charles Dibble. Journal articles and abstracts of papers. Copies of ECO, a bulletin from the Instituto Jalisciense de Antropologia e Historia. Programs and proceedings from The Southwest Conference.
- Course Notes, Bibliographies and Student Papers, circa 1920-1970 (Box 15)
  Twelve small notebooks and two folders of Anderson's course/lecture notes as a professor at San Diego State College. Two folders of American Southwest archaeology and ethnology notes for class. Anderson's Southwest culture bibliography. Anderson's class list for Sociology 150 Ethnography of Indians of American Southwest. Five student papers not returned to students in 1966. Copy of the Anales de Cuauh.
- Publications and Research Files, 1949-1980 (Box 16)
  Bulk of materials includes periodicals and research files concerning Sahagun and Nahuatl. Sahagun, Fr. Bernardino de. Historia general de las cosas de Nueva Espana. Partial facsimile edition from the Codices Matritenses in the Mexican language, Mixteca that are housed in the libraries of the Royal Palace and the Royal Academy of History. Madrid: Phototype of Hauser and Menet. Facsimile photographs of unknown imprint, Spanish and Nahuatl language. Facsimile photographs of documents from the Seville Archive related to Sahagun. Four research binders of articles and notes on Sahagun. Folder and binder on Nahuatl grammar and vocabulary
- Primeros Memoriales Research Files and Correspondence, circa 1980-1989 (Box 17)
  Manuscripts, typescripts, correspondence and research notes related to The Primeros Memoriales of Fray Bernardino de Sahagun. Materials include a copy of the original Sahagun Primeros Memoriales document, Anderson's annotated drafts and a Sahagun sermon in English and Nahuatl.
- Research Files, Publications, Microfilm, Slides and Negatives, 1958-1970 (Box 18)
  Three Library of Congress microfilm reels of Sahagun's Historia General De Las Cosas Nueva Espana. One film canister of the Codex Rios Tepetlaoxtoc and Alfonso Caso's interpretation of the Codex Bodley. Seven rolls of film from the Biblioteca Nacional. Two film canisters. Four boxes of slides. Eight sets of negatives.
  Research files include Anderson's notes on the Florentine Codex, Sahagun and the Xolotl Codex. Photostats from Charles Dibble on the Codex Borgia.
  Publications include the following: Benjamin Keen's "Readings in Latin-American civilication: 1492 to the present," Manuscritos de America por Jesus Dominguez Bordona (Tomo IX), Dental Radiography and Photography, Prehispanic Indian Dentistry, "Historical notes relating to the Pre-Columbian amber trade from Chiapas, Mexico" and "Archaeology of the Funeral Mound Ocmulgee."
- Correspondence and Research Files, 1961-1994 (Box 19)
  Research files on the Escalona sermons with related correspondence from Barry Sell and Stafford Poole. Research files on Codex Chimalpahin and related correspondence with Barry Sell. Research files on Sahagun and Sahagun's sermons, Ayer manuscript and Resurrection sermon. Typescripts of "Aztec Wives" and "The Goddess Within." Materials also include a copy of the Codice en Cruz and photostats of Mayan calendars, Spanish-Maya dictionary and "Vocabulario en la lengua Maya."
- Correspondence and Research Files, 1903-1913, 1957-1997 (Box 20)
  Correspondence concerning Anderson's teaching positions. Sahaguntine Triptych typescript. Anales del Museo Nacional de Arqueologia. Correspondence between Charles Dibble and the Library of Congress Hispanic Foundation. Rules of the Classical Nahuatl Language typescript. "Nahuatl Language Research Materials" file. Correspondence between Susan Schroeder and Christine Anderson. Anderson's Memorial invitation, copies of his obituaries and correspondence of condolence from Mexico's Ambassador to the United Nations, Dr. Miguel Leon-Portilla.
- Correspondence, Reprints and Photographs, 1956-1997 (Box 21)
  Correspondence and newspaper clippings concerning Anderson and Charles Dibble's Order of the Aztec Eagle award and Anderson's Order of Isabel the Catholic from the Spanish government. Annotated reprints and offprints addressed to Anderson from his colleagues. Black and white photographs of Anderson and Mexico's Ambassador to the United Nations, Dr. Miguel Leon-Portilla at the San Diego State University Student Union Hall. File of publications, articles and newsletters about the Florentine Codex. Copies of Anderson's Curriculum Vitae. Cal State University Master's theses of Maria Nissley and Alfred Frank Velsaco, approved by Anderson. Bound copy of Montezuma opera by Roger Sessions with inscription to Anderson. Anderson's address book.
- Correspondence, 1953-1995 (Box 22)
  Professional correspondence with colleagues and institutions including Charles Dibble, John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, The Del Amo Foundation, School of American Research, Comision de Intercambio Cultural entre Espana y los EEUU, San Diego State College, University of Utah and Susan Schroeder.
- Research Slides, 1958-1970 (Box 23)
  Two slide cases of images from the Florentine Codex. One slide case of Peruvian museum work. One slide case of Bodley Manuscripts, American Museum of Natural History, Madrid, Egerton. One slide case of Pintura del Governador, Zuni, Hopi, Apache and Isleta Indians. One slide case of prints from British Museum including views of Athens and Rome.
- Index Cards, Undated (Box 24)
  Materials include hand written research index cards, copies of cards from library catalogs and Anderson's address book.
- Florentine Codex Typescript, circa 1955-1971 (Box 25)
  Sahagun's Florentine Codex typescript for Books 1-5, 7, 9 and 12. These documents are heavily annotated by Anderson. Materials also include Anderson's research notebooks from the British Museum, Biblioteca Nacional and Archivo Historico Nacional.
- Scrapbook and Typescript, 1951-1987 (Box 26)
  Scrapbook of newspaper clippings, reviews, photographs of Anderson and Dibble and correspondence regarding the publication of Codex Florentine. Annotated Codex Florentine typescript.
- Typescripts, Photostats and Publications, 1921-1974 (Box 27)
  Photostats of the Selden Roll, an ancient Mexican picture manuscript held at Oxford's Bodleian Library. Florentine Codex photostat negatives. Manuscript photostats from the British National Museum. "Reglas de la Lengua Mexicana" manuscript photostats. Photographic reproduction of "La aparicion de nuestra senora de Guadalupe de Mexico...." Anderson's translation of the apparitions of Guadalupe. Unbound copy of "Catalogo alfabetico de nombres vulgares y cientificos de plantas que existen en Mexico." Mappe Quinatzin photostats. Sahagun Codex photostats. Codex photostats. Materials also include one of Anderson's Florentine Codex notebooks related to Nahuatl grammar and translations.
- Manuscripts and Research Files, 1940-1987 (Box 28)
  Copy and manuscript of Juan de San Antonio's letter on "Texcoco Episodes." Exercicio Quotidiano manuscript and appendix. Copy of Ayer MS #1486 with Additions and Appendix. Materials also include early manuscript drafts, related correspondence, translations, articles, research notes and School of American Research Annual Reports.
- Correspondence, Typescripts and Research Files, 1953-1996 (Box 29)
  Correspondence and Sahagun research materials.
- Correspondence and Research Files, 1969-1994 (Box 30)
  Typescripts of Psalmodia Christiana Y Sermona in Nahuatl and English. Correspondence includes letters from Charles E. Dibble. Research files on Sahagun, Codex Florentine and Psalmodia.
- Slides, Negatives and Film, circa 1960s (Box 31)
  One box of negatives and film related to Mexico and Sahagun. One slide case labeled "Mexican Codices. Sahagun, Spain."
- Morheme Map, Dictionary and Photostats, undated (Box 32)
  Molina - Campbell Morpheme Map and Nahuatl - English - Spanish Dictionary. Three folders of map photostats.
- Maps, undated (Box 33)
  A map of ancient Mexico City, a map of Sahagun village, Spain and a color photograph of Aztec Lily (Sprekelia formosissima).
- Monographs (Box 34, Box 35)
  Scope and Contents
  Materials from Anderson's library concerning pre-conquest Mexican history.
- Monographs (Box 36)
  Materials from Anderson's library concerning Aztec history.
- Monographs (Box 37, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40)
  Materials from Anderson's library concerning the Spanish conquest of Mexico.
- Monographs (Box 41)
  Materials from Anderson's library by Fray Bernardino de Sahagun.
- Monographs (Box 42, Box 43)
  Codices from Anderson's library.
- Monographs (Box 44)
  Dictionaries, grammar and vocabulary books from Anderson's library.
- Monographs (Box 45)
  Dictionaries from Anderson's library.
- Monographs (Box 46)
  Manuscript and historical document bibliographies from Anderson's library.
- Monographs (Box 47)
  Manuscript and historical document bibliographies, facsimiles of historical documents and materials concerning paleography from Anderson's library.
- Monographs (Box 48)
  Materials from Anderson's library concerning Nahuatl philosophy, religion, politics and culture.
- Monographs (Box 49)
  Materials from Anderson's library concerning theater and literature.
- Monographs (Box 50)
  Materials from Anderson's library concerning spirituality, religion and medicine.
- Monographs (Box 51)
  Materials from Anderson's library concerning art and architecture.
- Monographs (Box 52)
  Materials from Anderson's library concerning literature, music and textiles.
- Monographs (Box 53, Box 54)
  Materials from Anderson's library concerning Mexican anthropology and archaeology.
- Monographs (Box 55)
  Materials from Anderson's library concerning subjects such as Darwinism in Mexico, the history of the School of American Research, colonial mining communities and Guadalajara.
- Serials, 1963-1995 (Box 56)
  Estudios De Cultura Nahuatl: Indices Y Autores v. 1-10 (1974). Estudios De Cultura Nahuatl v. 4-14 (1963-1980), v. 16-23 (1983-1993), v. 25 (1995).
- Serials, 1946-1986 (Box 57)
  Proceedings (Pacific Coast Council on Latin American Studies) v. 12 (1985-1986). Revista de Indias v. 24: no. 95-96 (1964). Revista Espanola de Antropologia Americana v. 4 (1969). Revista Geografica Espanola no. 20 (1947). Revista Interamericana de Bibliografia v. 5: no. 3 (1955). Revista Mexicana de Estudios Antropologicos v. 15-20 (1958-1966). Tlalocan v. 2: no. 2-3 (1946-1947), v. 3: no. 1 (1949), v. 8-9 (1980-1982).
- Serials, 1938-1986 (Box 58)
  Abside: Revista de cultura Mexicana v. 2: no. 3 (1938), v. 4: no. 3, 5 (1940), v. 9: no. 1-4 (1945). Actas del XLI Congreso Internacional de Americanistas v. 1-3 (1975-1976). Actas y Memorias XXXVI Congreso Internacional de Americanistas v. 1-4 (1966). AAR Studies in Religion no. 3 (1972). Antropologia e historia v. 19: no. 1 (1967). Anthropos v. 68: no. 1-2 (1973). Anthropological papers (University of Utah) no. 1-8 (1950). Archivos Leoneses v. 7: no. 14 (1953), v. 9: no. 17 (1955). Anales del Instituto Nacional de Antropologia e Historia v. 3 (1947-1948). Archivos Nahuas v. 1 (1954). Cahiers du Monde Hispanique et Luso-Breslien v. 31 (1978). Current Anthropology v. 11: no. 3 (1970). Emerita v. 34: no. 2 (1966). Historicas no. 19 (1986). Language (Linguistic Society of America) v. 30: no. 1, pt. 2 (1954). Journal de la Societe des Americanistes v. 41: no. 2 (1952).